Guide to the Cuban Revolution Materials Collection, 1952-1964 RL.11187
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Cuban Revolution Materials collection
1952-1964
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.11187
3.0 Linear Feet
The Cuban Revolution Materials collection comprises assorted printed materials and serials publications regarding the Cuban Revolution of 1959, Fidel Castro's governance, and U.S. foreign policy in Cuba in the 1960s, especially the Bay of Pigs Invasion of April 1961. Committees and Organizations series contains assorted documents including leaflets, position statements, generated by pro-Cuba organizations based in major metropolitan areas, primarily New York City, in 1960 and 1961. Original sources are unknown; the collection was received as a transfer from the Duke University Library pamphlet collection.
Arrangement
Arranged by processor. Committees and Organizations series arranged by organization name. Assorted Printed Materials series arranged chronologically by publication date.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Cuban Revolution Materials Collection was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a transfer from Duke University Libraries in 2012.
Collection Overview
Collection arranged into two series, Committees and Organizations and Assorted Printed Materials. The first series comprises assorted documents from U.S.-based committees in support of the Cuban Revolution and critical of U.S. foreign policy. The Assorted Printed Materials series is comprised of single serials related to the Cuban Revolution and U.S. foreign policy in Cuba, especially the Bay of Pigs Invasion in the early 1960s. The collection was transferred to the Rubenstein Library from the Duke University Library pamphlet collection in 2012. Their original source or sources are unknown; however it is likely that materials were collected by the library to support student research in the 1960s. Most of the material is from 1960 and 1961, with a concentration of printed materials from April and May of 1961, around the time of the Bay of Pigs Invasion. Committees represented in the collection show a pro-Cuba agenda and include The Fair Play for Cuba Committee, The Truth About Cuba Committee, Young Socialists Alliance, and the Non-Violent Committee for Cuban Independence. Materials include leaflets, event flyers, newsletters and correspondence, committee resolutions, and other printed ephemera from their grassroots efforts to educate audiences about the actions of the U.S. military in Cuba.
Cuba -- History -- Revolution, 1959; Cuba -- Foreign relations -- United States; Truth About Cuba Committee; Castro, Fidel, 1926-
- Committees and Organizations, 1960-1964 and undated; 1
  Scope and Contents
  The Committees and Organizations Series contains assorted materials collected in the early 1960s about the Cuban Revolution and the U.S.'s foreign policy with Cuba, especially the Bay of Pigs Invasion. The materials represent small portions of materials generated by these committees and organizations, presumably collected for student research. The series mostly consists of leaflets, event flyers, newsletters and correspondence, recruitment materials, and position statements. The organizations and committees represented in the series are sympathetic to the Cuban Revolution and critical of the U.S. engagement against Castro's government. Organizations from across the country including the Truth About Cuba Committee, the Fair Play for Cuba Committee, the Young Socialists Alliance, and the Non-Violent Committee for Cuban Independence are represented in the series, though most are central to New York City.
  - Militant Labor Reform, undated (Box 1)
  - Labor Educational League, undated (Box 1)
  - Labor and People's Committee for May Day, undated (Box 1)
  - Socialist Workers Party, undated (Box 1)
  - Cuba and Nonviolence Open Forum, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Committee to Defend Francisco Molina, undated (Box 1)
  - Young Socialist Alliance, undated (Box 1)
  - CORNUCOPIA, undated (Box 1)
  - Organizing Committte to Reconstitute a Marxist-Leninist Party in the U.S. (Box 1)
  - Intelligence Digest, undated (Box 1)
  - Non-Violent Committee for Cuban Independence, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Young People's Socialist League, 1961 (Box 1)
  - On Guard for Freedom Committee, 1961 (Box 1)
  - The Truth About Cuba Committee, 1961-1964 and undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous event ephemera, undated (Box 1)
  - Fair Play for Cuba Committee, 1960-1961; 2
    - Constitution, by-laws, budgets, undated (Box 1)
    - Committee resolutions, 1961 (Box 1)
    - National Conference, Jul-61 (Box 1)
    - Recruitment materials, undated (Box 1)
    - Press releases, May - June 1961 (Box 1)
    - Newsletters and correspondence, 1961-1963 (Box 1)
    - Leaflets, undated (Box 1)
    - Event flyers, 1961 (Box 1)
    - Published pamphlets, undated (Box 1)
    - U.S. Senate International Security Sub-Committee, 1960-1961 (Box 1)
    - Other printed material, undated (Box 1)
    - Clippings, 1961 (Box 1)
- Assorted Printed Material, 1952-1961; 2
  The Assorted Printed Materials series contains assorted serials published around the time of the Cuban Revolution and Bay of Pigs Invasion, primarily in 1960 and 1961. All serials contain articles about the Cuban Revolution, Fidel Castro, and U.S. foreign policy with Cuba in the 1950s and early 1960s. Much of the material came from the prelude to and direct aftermath of the failed Bay of Pigs invasion in April 1961. Materials were originally housed in the library's pamphlet collection prior to transfer to the Rubenstein Library. Arranged chronologically. Some materials in Spanish.
  - Political Affairs, April 1952, January 1961, March 1961 (Box 2)
  - The Columbia Owl, Oct-60 (Box 2)
  - The Nation, January, July 1960 (Box 2)
  - U.S. News and World Report, Oct-60 (Box 2)
  - The New Leader, March 1958, July 1960, March-May 1961 (Box 2)
  - Hoy Domingo, Dec-60 (Box 2)
  - Salaciones del Reader's Indigest, Feb-60 (Box 2)
  - Saturday Review, Dec-60 (Box 2)
  - Contemporary Issues, Apr-60 (Box 2)
  - The New Republic, September, October 1960 (Box 2)
  - New York Times, 1960-1961 (Box 2)
  - Coronet, Jul-60 (Box 2)
  - Kulchur 2, 1960 (Box 2)
  - Politica, Jul-60 (Box 2)
  - The Young Socialist, 1960-1961 (Box 2)
  - Weekly People, Aug-60 (Box 2)
  - The Nation, 1961 (Box 2)
  - Dissent, Summer 1960 (Box 2)
  - Atlas, Mar-61 (Box 2)
  - Voz Proletaria, Mar-61 (Box 2)
  - El Mundo, May-61 (Box 3)
  - Encounter, Mar-61 (Box 2)
  - Village Voice, May-61 (Box 3)
  - The Catholic Worker, Apr-61 (Box 2)
  - The Second Coming, Jul-61 (Box 3)
  - New Horizons for Youth, Apr-61 (Box 3)
  - Monthly Review, January, April 1961 (Box 3)
  - Newsweek, January, May 1961 (Box 3)
  - Time, Apr-61 (Box 3)
  - The Minority of One, Apr-61 (Box 3)
  - International Socialist Review, Spring, Winter 1961 (Box 3)
  - Liberation, December 1960, April 1961 (Box 3)
  - Western Socialist, 1961 (Box 3)